<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<section id="section.about" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <title>About this specification</title>
  <!--======================================================================-->
  <section role="fragment">
    <title>Overview</title>
    <!--____________________________________________________________________-->
    <section role="specification">
      <title>Specification</title>
      <para>This specification details the format of CommonType fonts,
          the TrueType and CFF outline formats, and the TrueType
          hinting language. This document derives from Adobe's
          <link xlink:href="https://github.com/adobe-type-tools/aots">Annotated
          OpenType Specification</link>, a libre-licensed edition of the
          OpenType Specification version 1.4. The OpenType Specification was
          developed jointly by Adobe and Microsoft. Because OpenType is
          itself an extension of TrueType, there is also information in
          this document that was originally authored by Apple.</para>
      <para>Many references to both TrueType and PostScript exist
          throughout this document, as CommonType fonts combine the two
          technologies.</para>
      <para>If you have comments or suggestions about this document,
          please create an annotation by selecting the text on the page and
          pressing the "annotate" button. If you find errors or inaccuracies
          in this document, please <link xlink:href="https://github.com/commontype-standard/commontype-standard.github.io/issues/new">file
          an issue</link>.</para>
    </section>
    <!--____________________________________________________________________-->
    <section role="annotation">
      <title>Annotation</title>
      <para>The “Annotation” sections provides
          clarification of the published specification, sometimes by
          suggesting a different wording, sometimes by providing
          background information.</para>
    </section>
    <!--____________________________________________________________________-->
    <section role="xml-representation">
      <title>XML Representation</title>
      <para>The “XML representation” sections propose
         an XML representation of CommonType fonts. The mains goals are:
          <itemizedlist><listitem><para>allow the precise representation of fonts in an
                XML form, to facilitate exchange, manipulation by
                programs, or archival of fonts.</para></listitem><listitem><para>be a convenient form to author fonts or fragments
                of fonts; in particular, facilitate the creation of
                fonts to test CommonType engines.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para>
      <para>The XML representation is currently formalized in
          a Relax NG schema, expressed here in the compact syntax.</para>
    </section>
    <!--____________________________________________________________________-->
    <section role="compiler">
      <title>Compiler</title>
      <para>The “Compiler” sections are the source
        code for a compiler that converts from the XML representation
        to actual font files.</para>
    </section>
    <!--____________________________________________________________________-->
    <section role="decompiler">
      <title>Decompiler</title>
      <para>The “Decompiler” sections are the source
        code for a decompiler that converts from the actual font files
        to their XML representation.</para>
    </section>
    <!--____________________________________________________________________-->
    <section role="implementation">
      <title>Implementation</title>
      <para>The “Implementation” sections are the
        source code for classes that represent fonts, as well as
        support usual operations. For example, the implementation code
        for the <ottable>cmap</ottable> table includes method to
        convert a code point to a glyph ID.</para>
    </section>
    <!--____________________________________________________________________-->
    <section role="test-suite">
      <title>Test Suite</title>
      <para>The “Test Suite” sections are test fonts
        and test cases which exercise the implementation. As much as
        possible, those test cases have been designed to be usable
        with any implementation, assuming a test harness is
        provided.</para>
    </section>
    <!--____________________________________________________________________-->
    <section role="validation">
      <title>Validation</title>
      <para>The “Validation” sections are the source
          code for a font validator. The intent is that the validator
          would detect violation of the specification, as well as
          violation of additional rules and dubious constructs.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
